<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Doug Johnson&#39;s website</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Doug Johnson&#39;s website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dougj892&#34;&gt;Doug Johnson&lt;/a&gt; 2020. Site design by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ribic&#34;&gt;Emir Ribic</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>An Alternative Approach to Power Calculations</title>
      <link>/post/an-alternative-approach-to-power-calculations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/an-alternative-approach-to-power-calculations/</guid>
      <description>The typical approach to power calculations goes something like this: first, the evaluator estimates the smallest MDE for which the intervention would be cost-effective. Second, the evaluator calculates the sample required to detect that MDE. Third, the evaluator throws out the calculations from step two after realizing the evaluation would be way too expensive and instead estimates the MDE she can detect given her budget constraints.The problem with this approach is that it doesn’t take into account the cost of the evaluation itself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three Stage Sampling</title>
      <link>/post/3-stage/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/3-stage/</guid>
      <description>Caveat emptor: This blog post has not been thoroughly checked for errors.
One of IDinsight&amp;rsquo;s project teams is in the process of designing the sampling strategy for a large scale household survey and is considering using a three stage sampling design in which they would first select districts, then villages (or urban wards), and then households. In addition, someone was asking about three stage clustering for an RCT somewhere on Slack (I can&amp;rsquo;t seem to find the slack post now) so I thought it might be useful to write a short post on three stage designs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Random Sampling vs. PPS Sampling</title>
      <link>/post/srs-v-pps/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/srs-v-pps/</guid>
      <description>A question came up on one of our evaluations on whether we should use simple random sampling (SRS) or probability proportional to size (PPS) sampling when selecting villages (our primary sampling units) for a matching study. Under SRS, you randomly select primary sampling units (PSUs) until you reach your desired sample size. With PPS sampling, you select your PSUs using some measure of size. PPS is often used in a first stage of a two-stage sampling design because if you use PPS to select PSUs and then select a fixed number of units (households in our case) per PSU in the second stage of sampling, the probability of selection will be identical for all units.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fixed Effects vs Difference-in-Differences</title>
      <link>/post/fe-did/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/fe-did/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR: When you have longitudinal data, you should use fixed effects or ANCOVA rather than difference-in-differences since a difference-in-difference specification will spit out incorrect variance estimates. If the data is from a randomized trial, ANCOVA is probably a better bet.
Trying to understand when to use fixed effects and when to use difference-in-differences (DiD), in the past, always made me feel like an idiot. It seemed like I was missing something really obvious that everyone else was getting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web Scraping 101</title>
      <link>/post/web-scraping/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/web-scraping/</guid>
      <description>More and more organizations are publishing their data on the web. This is great, but often websites don’t offer an option to download a clean and complete dataset from the site. In this situation, you have two options. First, you (or some unlucky intern) can hunker down and spend a week wearing out the ‘c’ and ‘v’ keys on your keyboard as you cut and paste ad nauseam from the website to an Excel spreadsheet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Hypothesis Testing</title>
      <link>/post/mult-hypothesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/mult-hypothesis/</guid>
      <description>layout: post title: &amp;ldquo;Multiple Hypothesis Testing&amp;rdquo; date: 2016-07-04 10:40:48 -0400 categories: jekyll update This week, I volunteered to read and summarize one of the articles for IDinsigh&amp;rsquo;s tech team&amp;rsquo;s book club. The topic for this week is multiple hypothesis testing and the article I volunteered to summarize is &amp;ldquo;Multiple Inference and Gender Differences in the Effects of Early Intervention: A Reevaluation of the Abecedarian, Perry Preschool, and Early Training Projects&amp;rdquo; by Michael Anderson.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Response to Blattman&#39;s Post on Why What Works Is The Wrong Question</title>
      <link>/post/blattman/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/blattman/</guid>
      <description>Last week, Chris Blattman published a long blog post titled “Why ‘what works?’ is the wrong question: evaluating ideas not programs.” In the blog post, which was adapted from a talk he gave at DFID, Blattman argues that a) impact evaluations should focus on deeper, theory-driven questions rather than just whether a program works or not and b) researchers should design impact evaluations to allow for generalizability by paying attention to context and running multiple evaluations in multiple contexts.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>